Ira Eaker Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Ira Eaker Papers 1917-1989 (bulk 1942-1945)
MSS19331
Eaker, Ira, 1896-1987
77,300 items 218 containers plus 16 oversize and 2 classified 89.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States Army air corps officer, aviation pioneer, aircraft industry executive, and newspaper columnist. Part I consists of correspondence, memoranda, diaries, reports, meetings minutes, printed material, and other papers documenting Eaker's military career in the aeronautical section of the United States Army, particularly his experiences in World War II. Part II consists of correspondence, memoranda, diaries speeches, writings, and scheduling and subject files pertaining to Eaker's activities after leaving the military.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Arnold, Henry Harley, 1886-1950--Correspondence.; Cannon, Joseph K.--Correspondence.; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965--Correspondence.; Devers, Jacob L. (Jacob Loucks), 1887-1979--Correspondence.; Doolittle, James Harold, 1896-1993.; Douglas, Donald W. (Donald Wills), 1892-1981--Correspondence.; Eaker, Ira, 1896-1987.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969--Correspondence.; Fechet, James E. (James Edmond), 1877-; Fechet, James E. (James Edmond), 1877- --Correspondence.; Foulois, Benjamin Delahauf, 1879-1967.; Giles, Barney McKinney, 1892- --Correspondence.; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986--Correspondence.; Harris, Arthur Travers, Sir, 1892- --Correspondence.; Harris, Hunter--Correspondence.; Harte, Houston, 1893- --Correspondence.; Hughes, Howard, 1905-1976.; Hull, Harris B., 1909-1993--Correspondence.; Jackson, Glenn--Correspondence.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973--Correspondence.; Lay, Beirne, 1909- --Correspondence.; LeMay, Curtis E.--Correspondence.; Lovett, Robert A. (Robert Abercrombie), 1895-1986--Correspondence.; Parton, James, 1912- --Correspondence.; Pinkley, Virgil--Correspondence.; Quesada, Elwood R. (Elwood Richard), 1904- --Correspondence.; Rickenbacker, Eddie, 1890-1973--Correspondence.; Slessor, John Cotesworth, Sir, 1897- --Correspondence.; Spaatz, Carl, 1891-1974--Correspondence.; Speer, Albert, 1905-1981.; Twining, Nathan F. (Nathan Farragut), 1897-1982--Correspondence.; Twining, Nathan F. (Nathan Farragut), 1897-1982.; Westover, Oscar, 1883-1938.; Whitney, John Hay--Correspondence.
Organizations
Air Force Academy Foundation.; Air Force Historical Foundation.; Air University (U.S.). Air War College.; Douglas Aircraft Company.; Falcon Foundation.; Hughes Aircraft Company.; Hughes Tool Company.; Mediterranean Allied Air Forces.; North Atlantic Treaty Organization.; Strategic Arms Limitation Talks.; United States Air Force Academy.; United States. Air Force.; United States. Army Air Forces.; United States. Army Air Forces. Air Force, 8th; United States. Army Air Forces. Bomber Command, 8th.; United States. Army. Air Corps.; United States. Army. Air Service.
Subjects
Aeronautics, Military.; Aeronautics.; Air power.; Aircraft industry--United States.; Military readiness.; National security--United States.; Newspapers--Sections, columns, etc.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations.; World War, 1939-1945--Great Britain.; World War, 1939-1945--Italy.
Places
Europe--Description and travel.; Middle East.; Outer space--Exploration--United States.; Soviet Union--Defenses.; United States--Armed forces.; United States--Defenses.
Occupations
Air Force officers.; Army officers.; Aviators.; Executives.; Journalists.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Ira Eaker, army air corps officer, aviation pioneer, aircraft industry executive, and newspaper columnist, were given to the Library of Congress by Eaker between 1953 and 1962. Major additions to the collection were transferred to the Library from the Albert F. Simpson Historical Research Center, Maxwell Air Force Base, Alabama, from 1982 through 1984. Several smaller additions to the collection were donated by James Parton from 1985 through 1991.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Audiotapes have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Ira Eaker Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Ira Eaker are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified items in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified material.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1896, Apr. 13 Born, Field Creek, Tex.
1917 Joined Sixty-fourth Infantry Regiment, U.S. Army, El Paso, Tex.; appointed second lieutenant
1918 Flight instruction, Austin and Kelly Field, Tex.
1919-1921 Second and Third Aero Squadrons, Philippine Islands; promoted to captain
1922-1923 Commander, Fifth Aero Squadron and Post Adjutant, Mitchel Field, N.Y.
1923[?] Married Leah Chase (divorced 1930)
1923-1924 Studied contract law, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1924-1926 Executive assistant, Office of Air Service, Washington, D.C.
1926-1927 Pilot, Pan-American Goodwill flight around South America; received Distinguished Flying Cross
1927-1928 Executive officer, Office of Assistant Secretary of War, Washington, D.C.
1928-1932 Operations and line maintenance officer, Bolling Field, Washington, D.C.
1929, Jan. 1-7 Chief pilot, "Question Mark" refueling endurance flight; received oak leaf cluster to Distinguished Flying Cross
1931 Married Ruth Apperson
1934 B.A., University of Southern California, Los Angeles, Calif. Commanded Air Mail Route 4, Western Zone, army air corps mail operations
1934-1935 Commanded Thirty-fourth Pursuit Squadron and Seventeenth Pursuit Squadron, March Field, Calif.; promoted to major
1935-1936 Attended Air Corps Tactical School, Maxwell Field, Ala.
1940 Promoted to lieutenant colonel
1940-1941 Commander, Twentieth Pursuit Group, Hamilton, Tex.
1941-1942 Special duty, Royal Air Force (R.A.F.) to observe and fly new types of fighter planes and to observe British fighter control methods, England
1942 Organized and commanded Eighth Bomber Command
1942-1944 Commander, Eighth Air Force in England; commanding general, United States Army Air Forces in the United Kingdom
1944-1945 Air commander in chief, Mediterranean Allied Air Forces
1945 Deputy commander, army air forces, and chief of air staff
1946 Promoted to lieutenant general retroactive to 1 Dec. 1944
1947 Retired from military service
1947-1957 Vice president, Hughes Tool Co.; represented Hughes Tool Co. at Hughes Aircraft Company, Houston, Tex. (1947-1948) and Culver City, Calif. (1948-1957)
1957-1961 Vice president, eastern office, Douglas Aircraft Co., Washington, D.C.
1961-[?] Chairman, Advisory Board, Hughes Aircraft Co.
1962-1980 Wrote syndicated weekly newspaper column on national security issues
1972-1973 First president, United States Strategic Institute, which published the Strategic Review; later vice chairman and member, board of directors
1985 Awarded fourth star; made a full general as a result of special legislation
1987, Aug. 6 Died, Camp Springs, Md.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Ira Clarence Eaker (1896-1987) span the years 1917-1989, with a large portion concentrated in the World War II period, 1942-1945. The papers consist of two parts processed at different times which document two distinct phases of Eaker's life. Part I treats Eaker's military career in the United States Army Air Corps (1918-1947). Part II relates to Eaker's activities after leaving the military, including those as an aviation industry executive, spokesman for the air force and air power, and as a syndicated newspaper columnist who wrote and lectured on national security issues. Eaker maintained contact with military associates throughout his life, and the themes of air power, aviation, and belief in a strong national defense are prominent throughout the collection.
Part I
Part I of Eaker's papers documents nearly every aspect of his long career in the United States Army Air Corps and is especially comprehensive for the World War II years, when Eaker organized and commanded the Eighth Bomber Command in England and commanded the Eighth Air Force, United States Army Air Forces, in the United Kingdom and the Mediterranean Allied Air Forces (MAAF) in Italy. Eaker led the first American B-17 bomber strike against German occupation forces in France, bombing Rouen in 1942. He was a key proponent of precision daylight bombing attacks on Germany's industrial war production, and in 1944 while commanding the MAAF he led the first shuttle bombing raid from Italy into Germany, landing in the Soviet Union after striking German targets. Eaker's final positions in Washington, D.C., as chief of air staff and then as deputy chief of army air forces involved demobilization of the air forces and planning for the creation of the air force as a separate branch of the military service.
The Diaries series contains typescript accounts of Eaker's activities in the military for the period 1942-1947, including his military service in World War II and his work in Washington until his retirement. The diaries include Eaker's daily schedule and record his flying time. Details are more official than personal.
The Personal File comprises Eaker's files relating to his military career prior to World War II. Personal correspondence and official documents depict the growth and promotion of military aviation. During the late 1920s and 1930s, Eaker was a pioneering aviator who made test flights and successful and unsuccessful attempts at aerial records. The files for March-May 1934 cover the period when the army air corps transported mail following the cancellation of commercial airmail contracts by President Franklin D. Roosevelt. Eaker commanded the operations of Air Mail Route 4, Western Zone.
The General Correspondence series contains correspondence of a personal and general nature for the period 1942-1950. The correspondence for the war years complements the official material in the World War II File.
Although material relating to World War II can be found in almost every series in Part I, the World War II File contains Eaker's extensive working files relating to his establishment of the Eighth Bomber Command in England in 1942 and his command of the Eighth Air Force in the United Kingdom in 1943 and the Mediterranean Allied Air Forces in Italy in 1944 and early 1945. Files for the Eighth Bomber Command and the Eighth Air Force document the American program of daylight strategic bombing of Germany and Eaker's close working relationship with the Royal Air Force. Topics covered in the Mediterranean Allied Air Forces files include the invasion of southern France, the strategic bombing offensive against German oil supplies, and shuttle bombing missions. Types of material include correspondence and memoranda between officers and military units, correspondence with families of missing aircrew men, bombing reports, and minutes of meetings.
The Subject File features notable events in Eaker's career as a pioneering aviator in the army air corps, including the Pan-American Goodwill Flight around South America (1926-1927), the refueling-endurance flight of the "Question Mark" (1929), and the operation of an air mail route in 1934 as well as flight records for his entire military career. Other material pertains to Eaker's activities with a variety of organizations relating to military and civil aviation.
The Speeches and Writings series contains articles, books, speeches, and associated material relating to speaking engagements. Principal themes are aviation, air power, and national security. In addition to articles and speeches prepared and delivered by Eaker, other speeches and articles seem to have been prepared by Eaker for such individuals as chiefs of the Army Air Corps James E. Fechet and Oscar Westover. Book files include sections on Army Flyer and Winged Warfare, which Eaker coauthored with Henry Harley Arnold.
Prominent correspondents in this portion of the collection include Henry Harley ("Hap") Arnold, Joseph K. Cannon, Winston Churchill, Jacob L. Devers, James E. Fechet, Barney M. Giles, W. Averell Harriman, Arthur Harris, Robert A. Lovett, John C. Slessor, Carl A. Spaatz, and Nathan F. Twining.
Part II
The second part of the Eaker Papers begins with diaries containing brief accounts of daily activities, including meetings and events. The Scheduling File and the appointments and phone messages in the Subject File complement this series by supplying similar information and lengthening the period of time documented.
The General Correspondence documents Eaker's activities following the Second World War. Correspondence from the late 1940s through the 1950s concerns his career with Hughes Tool Company and Hughes Aircraft Company, first in Houston, Texas, and then in California. Correspondence relates to social and philanthropic activities on behalf of the Hughes organization, as well as to Eaker's contact with wartime colleagues. Eaker also reviewed the script for the movie "Twelve O'Clock High," written by Bierne Lay and Sy Bartlett, who had served in the Eighth Air Force in Britain during the war. Beginning in 1957, Eaker was based in Washington, D.C., where he served as East Coast representative of Douglas Aircraft and later on the advisory board of Hughes Aircraft, using his access to Defense Department officials to learn about policy and future expenditures. Correspondence after the early 1960s often contains comments on Eaker's national security columns. Eaker maintained long-lasting correspondence with wartime friends and coworkers and the letters record their periodic reunions. Well documented is his close friendship with Carl A. (Tooey) Spaatz. Other prominent and frequent correspondents in this portion of the collection include Donald Douglas, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Hunter Harris, Houston Harte, Harris Hull, Glenn Jackson, Lyndon B. Johnson (1950s), Bierne Lay, Curtis LeMay, James Parton, Virgil Pinkley, Elwood R. (Pete) Quesada, Eddie Rickenbacker, Sir John C. Slessor, and John Hay (Jock) Whitney.
The Scheduling File records Eaker's activities in the period 1952-1982 in correspondence, agendas, and other material relating to speaking engagements, ceremonial events, trips, conferences, and board meetings. Frequent activities include attendance at Air Force Logistics Command (AFLC) commanders' conferences, Air Force senior statesmen briefings at the Pentagon, visits to the Air Force Academy, lectures to classes at the Air War College of the Air University at Maxwell Air Force Base in Alabama, and speaking engagements for the Air Force, civic organizations, and other groups. In the 1970s, Eaker and Arthur Metcalf of the United States Strategic Institute made several trips to Europe, where Eaker visited World War II acquaintances in Britain, including Sir Arthur Harris and Sir John C. Slessor. He was briefed at North Atlantic Treaty Organization headquarters in Brussels, and visited Albert Speer, Hitler's minister of armament production, in Germany. In 1976, Eaker interviewed Speer about the air war in World War II and subsequently spoke and wrote about these conversations. Copies of Eaker's speeches are contained in the Speeches and Writings File.
Also in the Speeches and Writings File are copies of Eaker's articles, book reviews, syndicated news columns, and speeches. Major topics are aviation, air power, and national security. Eaker's newspaper columns span two decades, 1962-1980. First syndicated by the Copley News Service and then by the Los Angeles Times Syndicate of the General Features Corporation, the columns cover such topics as defense budgets, assessments of administrations from Kennedy through Reagan on national security issues, the Vietnam War, the military strength of the United States and the Soviet Union, the space program, the Middle East, and the Strategic Arms Limitation Talks (SALT). Eaker's speeches focus primarily on aviation and national security. They also include recollections of military leaders such as James H. Doolittle, James E. Fechet, Benjamin Foulois, Nathan F. Twining, Oscar Westover, and businessmen such as Howard Hughes. Many of the books Eaker reviewed related to World War II and prominent individuals he knew, such as Winston Churchill and Dwight D. Eisenhower.
The Subject File contains correspondence, reports, minutes, clippings, and printed matter relating to Eaker's involvement with the air force and the Air Force Academy and organizations such as the Falcon Foundation, the Air Force Academy Foundation, and the Air Force Historical Foundation. Other files concern the Hughes Aircraft Company and Donald W. Douglas (1892-1981) and Donald W. Douglas (1917- ), of Douglas Aircraft, as well as Eaker's dealings with Congress during the early 1960s. Similar subjects are covered in the Subject File of Part I, with overlap between the first and second portions of the collection in the late 1940s and early 1950s.
The James Parton File consists of papers accumulated by Eaker's wartime aide and biographer covering the last years of the general's life. Correspondence relates to the preparation of Parton's book, "Air Force Spoken Here": General Ira Eaker and the Command of the Air. Since Eaker was in failing health during the preparation of the biography, 1984-1986, much of Parton's correspondence is addressed to Ruth Eaker. During these last years of Eaker's life, Parton helped by answering correspondence and assisting with the disposition of the general's medals, uniforms, and memorabilia.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is organized in two parts composed of sixteen series:
Part I:
Diaries, 1942-1947
Personal File, 1926-1941
General Correspondence, 1942-1950
World War II File, 1937-1946
Subject File, 1918-1960
Speeches and Writings, 1918-1959
Oversize, circa 1926-1955
Classified, 1943-1946
Part II:
Diaries, 1958-1974
General Correspondence, 1940-1981
Scheduling File, 1952-1982
Speeches and Writings File, 1929-1981
Subject File, 1927-1985
James Parton File, 1917-1989
Oversize, 1930-1967
Classified, 1952-1978
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm79019331
Container List
- Part I: Diaries, 1942-1947 (Box I:1)
  Typescript notes of appointments with comments and a few collateral documents.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1942-1947, (7 folders) (Box I:1)
- Part I: Personal File, 1926-1941 (Box I:2-6)
  Personal and official correspondence.
  - Sept. 1926-Aug. 1928, (10 folders) (Box I:2)
  - Sept. 1928-Oct. 1930, (7 folders) (Box I:3)
  - Nov. 1930-Oct. 1935, (10 folders) (Box I:4)
  - Mar. 1936-Dec. 1939, (10 folders) (Box I:5)
  - Jan. 1940-Dec. 1941, (10 folders) (Box I:6)
- Part I: General Correspondence, 1942-1950 (Box I:7-16)
  Correspondence sent and received.
  - Jan. 1942-Jan. 1943, (10 folders) (Box I:7)
  - Feb.-June 1943, (10 folders) (Box I:8)
  - July-Oct. 1943, (9 folders) (Box I:9)
  - Nov. 1943-Feb. 1944, (10 folders) (Box I:10)
  - Mar.-Sept. 1944, (10 folders) (Box I:11)
  - Oct. 1944-May 1945, (10 folders) (Box I:12)
  - June 1945-Mar. 1946, (10 folders) (Box I:13)
  - Apr.-Dec. 1946, (10 folders) (Box I:14)
  - Jan.-May 1947, (9 folders) (Box I:15)
  - June 1947-Apr. 1950, (8 folders) (Box I:16)
- Part I: World War II File, 1937-1946 (Box I:16-36)
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, meeting minutes, press releases, notes, lists, accounts, and printed matter relating primarily to Eaker's command of the Eighth Bomber Command, the Eighth Air Force, and the Mediterranean Allied Air Forces.
  Largely organized under the name of these organizations and therein by type of material or topic, with the correspondence arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent or headquarters. Most files are in reverse chronological order and contain indexes.
  - Eighth Air Force (Box I:16)
    - Correspondence
      - Army Air Forces headquarters, Washington, D.C., 1942-1944, (2 folders)
      - Arnold, Henry Harley, 1942-1944, (5 folders) (Box I:17)
      - Complimentary letters, 1942-1944
      - Eighth Air Force commands, 1942-1943, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box I:18)
      - Eighth Air Force headquarters, 1942-1945, (6 folders)
      - Eubank, E. L., and George E. Stratemeyer, 1942-1943 (Box I:19)
      - European Theater of Operations, United States Army (ETOUSA), 1942-1943, (4 folders)
      - Giles, Barney M., 1943-1944, (2 folders)
      - Lovett, Robert A., 1943-1944
      - Miscellaneous correspondents, 1942-1943 (Box I:20)
      - Royal Air Force
        - Air Ministry, British War Cabinet, miscellany, 1942-1944, (2 folders)
        - Officers
          - Miscellaneous, 1942-1944, (2 folders)
          - Portal, Charles, 1942-1944
          - Trenchard, Hugh Montague, 1943-1944
      - Spaatz, Carl A., 1942-1943
      - Stratemeyer, George E. See Container I:19, Eubank, E. L., and George E. Stratemeyer
    - "Eighth Air Force Data," unpublished report, 1942-1945, undated, (7 folders) (Box I:21)
    - Financial records, 1942-1944, undated, (3 folders)
    - Maps and plans, 1941, undated See Part I: Oversize
    - Meetings, 1942-1943, (2 folders)
    - Miscellany, 1943-1944, undated See also Part I: Oversize, (3 folders) (Box I:22)
    - Press conferences, 1943
    - Public relations, 1942-1943
    - Reports
      - "Bi-monthly Report of Bombing Results," 1943 See Part I: Oversize
      - Miscellaneous, 1943-1945 See also Part I: Oversize
      - Royal Air Force, 1937-1943, (3 folders)
    - Writings on air power, 1942-1943, undated (Box I:23)
  - Eighth Bomber Command, 1942, (4 folders)
  - Mediterranean Allied Air Forces
    - Correspondence
      - Air Transport Command, 1945
      - Army Air Forces
        - Headquarters, Washington, D.C., 1944-1945, (2 folders)
        - Mediterranean Theater of Operations, 1944-1945, (2 folders) (Box I:24)
      - Arnold, Henry Harley
        - General, 1943-1945, (6 folders)
        - "Roundups," 1944-1945 See also Part I: Oversize, (2 folders)
      - Balkan Air Force, Brazilian Air Force, Coastal Air Force, Desert Air Force, and French Air Force, 1944-1945
      - Complimentary letters, 1944-1945 (Box I:25)
      - Devers, Jacob L. See Container I:27, Sixth Army Group
      - Families of missing aircrew men, 1944-1945
      - Fifteenth Air Force, 1944-1945, (3 folders)
      - Fifth Army, Seventh Army, Eighth Army, 1944
      - Giles, Barney M., 1944-1945, (4 folders)
      - Harriman, W. Averell, 1944-1945 (Box I:26)
      - Lovett, Robert A., 1944-1945
      - Mediterranean Allied Air Forces
        - Headquarters, 1944-1945, (7 folders)
        - Rear echelon, Algiers, 1944, (2 folders) (Box I:27)
      - North African Theater of Operations, United States Army (NATOUSA), 1944
      - Office of Strategic Services (OSS), 1944-1945
      - Royal Air Force
        - Portal, Charles, and Trenchard, Hugh Montague, 1944-1945
        - Slessor, John, 1944-1945, (2 folders)
      - Sixth Army Group, Jacob L. Devers, 1944-1945
      - Spaatz, Carl A. See Container I:28, United States Strategic Air Forces in Europe
      - Supreme Allied Headquarters, 1944-1945, (2 folders)
      - Twelfth Air Force, 1944-1945, (2 folders) (Box I:28)
      - United States Strategic Air Forces in Europe (USSTAF), 1944-1945, undated, (5 folders)